Hello, class. This lecture will
focus on the
pharmacology of CHF.
And CHF, very simply, is a
decrease in cardiac output.
And that decrease in
cardiac output means
that blood is not
flowing through the body,
not delivering oxygen
to where it's needed.
And oftentimes,
when this worsens,
there's a chance
that the patient
does not make it,
does not survive.
There are certain drugs
that are used to manage
chronic congestive heart
failure. There will
be a few that we'll go
over that can manage
acute congestive heart
failure or decompensated
congestive heart failure.
Those are mainly going
to be the positive
inotropes like dobutamine.
I will go through
the mechanisms of
action of these drugs
and with that the
adverse effects and
drug interactions.
So, a decrease in cardiac
output, number one, is
going to result in a decrease
in carotid sinus firing.
And that now depends, going
back to what we talked
about early on, that when
your body is sensing a
decrease in your heart rate
or blood pressure, what
it's going to do is
invoke sympathetics. and
that increase of norepinephrine
is going to increase
the force of contraction,
increase the rate, and
increase preload. And that
would make sense if you
are talking about somebody
with a failing heart.
On the flip side,
there's also a
decrease in blood
flow to the kidneys.
And when that is sensed,
what gets invoked is RAS.
So renin, angiotensin,
and aldosterone. You can
see that angiotensin II is
a potent vasoconstrictor
and that's going to
increase both afterload and
remodeling. And these
are things that are not
favorable to the patient.
So remember, with preload,
that has to do with the
amount of venous return
to the heart. And how we
manage high preload is by
giving something that
works on the venous side.
That can be isosorbide.
That can be something
like nitroprusside.
Afterload has to do
with, now, the amounts
of pressure the
ventricles need to
overcome to push the
blood to the aorta.
What works nicely there
is going to be something
that has an arterial
vasodilator effect. That could
be something like
hydrolazine. Or it could also
be an ACE inhibitor or an
ARB. And that is probably
one of the reasons why
these drugs are so widely
used for chronic
congestive heart failure.
Because they can decrease
angiotensin, decrease
aldosterone, decrease preload,
and decrease afterload.
From the side of sympathetic
overdrive, this is
where we start to understand
the benefit of beta
blockers. Because beta
blockers, what they will
do is they will bind to
the beta receptors, beta
-1 receptors in the heart
and block norepinephrine.
So you'll see in the
mainstream right now of
congestive heart failure,
what's widely used is
going to be the RAS drugs
and the beta blockers.
so basically just to
summarize chf is the
inability of the ventricle
to pump blood into the
circulation and this
is why the the state of
the left ventricle is
very important that's why
doctors will order
echocardiograms to check
the left ventricle they
want to check the ejection
fraction because if
the ejection fraction
is low that is going
to result now in the
patient having all symptoms
of a failing heart.
Why does congestive
heart failure happen?
It could be due to
a recent or past MI.
patients who don't get well
control of their hypertension.
And remember, BP equals
cardiac output times stroke
volume. And remember,
stroke volume is another
important term. This is
the amount of blood that
gets let out of the left
ventricle per every heartbeat.
So these terms are very
important. They're a good
time to review, especially
when we want to connect
the drugs. And then
also arrhythmias can lead
to congestive heart failure.
Somebody who does not
have well control of their
AFib may end up getting
congestive heart failure.
There are also certain
drugs that can induce heart
failure. Number one
doxorubicin and this was
reviewed last spring in the
anti-neoplastic lecture.
Doxorubicin is an
intercalating agent and that's
going to get in between
the strands of the DNA
ladder so to speak and
cause breaks. The other
thing is that there's an
induction of ROSs, which
can break the DNA strands
that are in the cancer
cell, but they also
affect some of the normal
cells, like the contractile
proteins of the heart.
So you'll see that
oftentimes patients that have
been treated with doxorubicin
will develop something
called dilated
cardiomyopathy. And the way I
remember doxirubicin is that
it's ruby red. So forever,
I will always remember
that doxy is cardiotoxic.
Diazolidinidones
or the glitazones
are PPAR gamma agonists.
And you saw PPAR-alpha not
too long ago when we talked
about VLDL and fibrates.
for this particular drug
group, they will enhance
GLUT4. And GLUT4 is going to be
responsible for pulling up
glucose into the fat and
muscle tissue and that itself
will improve resistance.
But on the side of
a person with CHF,
these drugs can
also enhance ENAC,
epithelial sodium channels
in the collecting duct.
And if that is happening,
you're going to recover
more sodium and water
and create more edema.
NSAIDs can also have an
effect on congestive heart
failure and blood pressure
to an extent because
they are responsible for
blocking prostaglandins
in the afferent arteriole.
And that is going to
lead to vasoconstriction,
reduced blood flow in
the kidney, and that's
going to reduce your GFR.
All of this put
together is going
to result in
cardiac remodeling.
Remodeling is not a
positive term, so to speak.
This is where now muscle
is going to be replaced
by fibrin and collagen
and that is going to
affect, of course, the
stiffness of the ventricles.
So cardiac remodeling is
especially a problem after
somebody has an MI That's
why it's very critical
that a patient gets to
the ED as soon as possible
There's going to be a
stretch in the fibers You're
going to get fibrosis,
deposition of collagen And
that's going to reduce
the stroke volume and the
cardiac output It's going
to decrease contractility
And as I said, that
is all due to the fact
that the ventricles
now are going to
become stiff because you're
getting a replacement
of muscle with
fibrin and collagen.
So you'll see that the
resulting enhancement of
sympathetics and the
resulting enhancement of RAS
really is what makes,
again, The beta blockers
and the ACE inhibitors
and all that group so
valuable in maintaining
somebody with chronic CHF.
Very simply,
left ventricular failure
is where the heart
can't maintain the
body's blood flow needs.
And you're going
to see that the
patient will develop
edema, edema,
difficulty breathing,
orthopnea, which means
that they need several
pillows to feel better
when they're lying down,
fatigue, hypoxia, and
ultimately organ dysfunction.
Right ventricular
failure is when the right
ventricle, now think about
the anatomy of the heart,
can't pump blood to the
lungs, and there's going to be
now some edema in that area.
And you'll see that the
patient can have ankle edema.
And then post-mortem has
observed that patients will
now present with nutmeg
liver. And this has to do
with the fact that there is
such a decrease in blood
flow, a decrease in oxygen,
that the liver now starts to
to get an oxidative event.
I don't want to talk
about the symptoms and
the signs, but it does
make sense that patients
will start to feel like
they can't breathe,
whether they can't
breathe when they're
lying down, they
might be coughing,
they may start to have
episodes of nausea and
vomiting, They may be
anxious, whether it's due
to the fact that
sympathetics are invoking
this anxiety or simply
due to the fact that if
you can't breathe, you're
going to be anxious.
Patients will also
be more tired. These
patients are at a higher
risk of getting anemia.
And also when you
listen to the patient's
heart, not only will they
be tachycardic, you'll
also hear something
called an S3 gallop.
the frank starling law
is is a very important
concept in cardiac physiology
I won't test you on
it but just so that you
understand that on the
x-axis that implies
venous return which is the
preload and the y-axis
implies stroke volume which
is again the amounts
of blood that the left
ventricle will pump out
per heartbeat and it shows
you that the more the
higher the venous return
the higher the stroke volume
and that makes sense okay
it's almost like saying
increasing the stretch is
going to increase the force
of contraction it's like as
much as you give in you're
going to get out think of it
as a rubber band if you
stretch a rubber band halfway
and you let it go, the
rubber band is going to snap
back to where you pulled
it. If you pull the rubber
band even farther and you
let it go, now it's going to
take more time for it to go
back to what it was, okay?
And basically what
this is saying is that
when patients have
systolic failure, you
can see here in the
red line, this is the
relationship of preload
to stroke volume.
And if you give a
positive inotropic drug,
that's going to bring
the line now halfway
between the normal
and systolic failure.
Management of CHF, diet,
exercise, and sodium
restriction guidelines,
which has changed,
will be covered, I
believe, by Dr. Yusupov.
But for pharmacology, if
we're decreasing the preload,
we want to use a diuretic,
an ACE inhibitor, an
ARB, or a venodilator. So
something like nitroprusside
or something like isosorbide.
If you want to decrease
afterload, you can give
an ACE inhibitor, an ARB,
or ARB, and an arterial
vasodilator like hydrolazine.
So again, this is why ACE,
ARBs, ARNIs are so good
for CHF because they can
decrease both preload and
afterload to improve
contractility you can give a
beta 1 agonist mainly dig
could work but it has many
adverse effects and drug
interactions and also the pde3
blockers which I'll cover
momentarily for remodeling
it's the rash drugs and
the beta blockers again
very widely used you should
put that in your in your
minds for as of now that's
what we're using for
maintaining somebody with chf
and then remember it's not
just a one shot deal
usually if somebody has chf
they probably had an mi in
the past they probably have
hyperlipidemia they probably
have had type 2 diabetes
so it's going to be a
challenge in that you're
going to have to deal with
many drugs on board so
understanding their mechanism
and the adverse effects and
the drug interactions will
be very, very critical.
Positive inotropic
drugs are not
going to be used for every day.
They're going to increase
contractility. They're
going to be for acute
compensated heart failure.
Sometimes we can use, especially
dobutamine, if we have
a patient that is going
into shock. So these are not
going to be something that
you're going to do widely.
Digoxin can be used,
and in the past,
digoxin was used, but
we had so many newer
drugs come to market,
all the RAS drugs.
We had now studies saying
that beta blockers were
actually a good thing, so
digoxin is not as widely used.
Again, we will review this
medication as we did in
the antiarrhythmic lecture,
but it's not widely used.
Dopamine is interesting
because, as mentioned,
these patients that have CHF
will start to see trouble
with their kidneys, especially
if we're talking about
an elderly patient. So
dopamine does maintain
glomerular filtration rate
and also the renal blood flow.
And then milrinone is an
indirect drug that will,
in fact, be a PDE3
inhibitor. Because remember,
with dobutamine, given
the fact that it's a
beta agonist and has a
G-stimulatory mechanism,
this medication is going
to increase cyclic AMP.
And that is going to lead
now to an increase in
protein kinase A, increase
in calcium, and that's
going to cause an improvement
in the contractility.
Milrinone, being a PDE3
blocker, does so indirectly
because it blocks the
breakdown of protein kinase A.
So let's first review digoxin.
Digoxin, as you can
see in this picture,
and we went through
this not too long ago,
This medication is
going to inhibit an
enzyme known as sodium
-potassium ATPase.
And by doing that, it's
going to affect the exchange
between sodium and calcium.
Because remember, with
that mechanism, for every
three sodium that come in, one
calcium is going out. Once
you block this enzyme and
this exchanger is affected,
sodium now starts to
accumulate into the cell.
And with it, so does calcium.
So now you have calcium
in the cell, in the
myocyte, and that's going
to cause an increase
in contraction. That's
a positive inotropic.
So remember, inotropic
is contractility.
Coronotropic is heart rate.
So DIG has a long half
-life. It also has a narrow
therapeutic index. okay so
even a small increase in
digoxin can lead to toxicity
in patients they're just
negative chronotropic so
if this is going to bring
down the heart rate because
of the parasympathetic
mechanism that it has
through the vagus the other
thing to know is that digoxin
can cause something known
as an after depolarization
and that happens right
after phase three of the
action potential during phase
four and it has to do with
the fact that there is
so much calcium coming
into the cell that you're
going to get this after
depolarization okay that makes
sense and the reason that
this usually happens is
when the patient is
hypokalemic, okay? And this used
to be a problem because
when patients were in CHF,
oftentimes you have
to give diuretics, and
we'll go through them
a little bit later.
And the one that
they like to use is
the high-ceiling one,
which is furosemide.
Furosemide gets rid
of everything, sodium
water, magnesium, and
calcium, and potassium.
This mechanism is potentiated
in states of low potassium.
So lots of calcium will
be here. And then after
phase three repolarization,
you're going to
get an after depolarization.
And that could lead
to something known as
torsades. And the way
we manage, remember from
the previous lecture,
either we have to give and
rectify the low potassium.
and we also would give
magnesium to kind of
shuttle out that calcium
that is inside the myocyte.
Digoxin comes from
this nice pinkish
purple plant that's
called foxglove.
And on an EKG, digoxin
can sometimes show
as an increase in PR
and that has to do with
the fact that it's an
AV node suppressant.
Why? Because of the negative
coronotropic effects.
And the other thing
that you might see, and
again, it's not something
that is a danger,
but it kind of shows
the physician that the
patient is on the doxin,
is this ST depression.
It's known sometimes as a
hockey stick configuration,
and that has to do with
the fact that you're
getting a flattened T
-wave, as you can see here.
Digoxin can cause
nausea, vomiting,
diarrhea, and a
loss of appetite.
Ventricular arrhythmia
has to do with those
patients that have electrolyte
imbalances. So again,
if you're taking
furosemide and digoxin, you
need to watch that
patient's potassium level.
digoxin or foxglove the way
we remember the toxicity
with the yellow halos
is through the Van Gogh
effect where they said
that Van Gogh was using
digitalis for some type of
condition and they think
that he was taking too
much and that's why he
painted his paintings yellow
whether that's true or
not I'm not sure but it
does help remember the
yellow halos And that is
due to the fact that in the
retina pigment epithelial
cells, there's a blockade
of the sodium potassium
ATPase in that area.
Gynecomastia is due
to the fact that if
you look at estrogen
and digoxin's structure,
they're almost alike.
So some patients,
especially males,
can experience
some enlargement
in their chest.
Digoxin is a weak
acid. If you gave, say,
calcium carbonate for
GERD and now the area is
alkalinized and you gave
digoxin, there's going
to be something called
ionization of the DIG.
and that would mean that
digoxin does not get
absorbed because remember,
in order to get absorption
you have to have the
drug being non-ionized.
Cholestyramine is a bile
acid resin and back to when
we talked about lipids if
you inhibit entero hepatic
circulation of bile acids
that means more of it is going
to show up in your feces
And now to recover and make
more bile acids, you have
to use up your cholesterol.
And that's a good thing.
Some lowering of LDL,
not as great as statins,
obviously. But the other
thing is that bile acid resins
can also bind other
medications, whether that is
this medication or thyroxine
or fat-soluble vitamins.
So the idea here is you
will need to space this out
by several hours. The DIG
and the bile acid resin.
Amiodarone, probably
the mechanism there
is the fact that
it's a SIP inhibitor.
Remember, amiodarone is liver.
And if it inhibits
metabolism of
digoxin, it can
raise DIG levels.
For verapamil and quinidine,
what will happen is
you're going to get an
inhibition of P-glycoproteins
and that's going to decrease
the digoxin's clearance.
That's going to lead to
more digoxin. So again,
you have to be very careful
with the digoxin level.
Anybody that has a renal
impairment or an elderly
patient is going to have
reduced DIG elimination.
So the dosing for
certain populations,
like the elderly,
like the renal
impaired, has to be
different, lower.
And then the antidote.
If you ingested a large
amount, you could bind the
medication with DigFab.
Some protocols say
cholestyramine, but I don't
think it's as good as
DigFab or Digibind. And the
other thing is you want to
manage the electrolytes.
Because remember, the
after depolarizations
are going to make
the patient at a
greater risk for getting
a torsades event.
So you could also
give the magnesium.
Increased cyclic
AMP is going to be
the goal of both
direct and indirect.
Direct is going to be
dobutamine. That is a
direct-acting beta-1
agonist, G-stimulatory.
You see it right here.
That's going to increase adenyl
cyclase, increase cyclic AMP,
increase protein kinase
A, and now you're getting
calcium in. That's going to
increase your contractility.
Perfect.
Milrinone is going to do
so indirectly, that it
inhibits phosphodiesterase
3. And by doing that,
you're going to enhance
your protein kinase A, and
the same outcome is going
to be on contractility.
So remember,
PDE3, milrinone, PDE5, that
was the drugs like ******,
Sildenafil,
Vodafinil, and those,
remember, applied to
nitrates. And I will
review this point
coming up anyway.
So the razoidilators.
chronic CHF, ACE
inhibitors, ARBs,
ARNIs,
hydralazine, which can also be
somewhat arterial
vasodilator as well.
And the other thing is
nitric oxide donors.
So anything like nitroglycerin,
isosorbide, nitroprusside.
okay so angiotensinogen
is made in the liver by
the action of renin it
gets converted to angio one
and by the action of
angiotensin converting enzyme
it makes angio two angio
two number one is a
potent vasoconstrictor
so blood pressure will go
up it does have some role
in sympathetic transmission.
It's going to increase
also the heart rate.
And then vasopressin, due
to the fact that you're
getting ADH release from
the posterior pituitary,
is going to increase sodium
and water permeability,
and that's going to
enhance blood volume.
And the other thing with
this is also aldosterone.
Aldosterone is coming from
the adrenal cortex, and
that's going to do the
same thing. It increases
blood volume because
aldosterone holds in more salt
and water. So all that
together is going to be the
compensatory mechanism
that is given by the kidney
in those that have
CHF. So what do we do?
Well, we will block
certain things here.
We can block renin with
alaskirin, and this is not
really given as first line.
Usually if the patient is
after a while not responding
to an ACE inhibitor or ARB,
they may give alaskirin as
the direct renin binder.
But we tend to use
ACE inhibitors.
Those are all the PRILs,
enalapril,
captopril,
ramipril,
okay? You block this
enzyme, you don't make angio
-2. And now downstream, all
of this will be reduced.
Decrease angio-2,
decrease aldosterone,
decrease the ADH
release and vasopressin.
But ACE is responsible
for breaking down a
pro-inflammatory mediator
known as bradykinin.
Bradykinin, if it's
not broken down,
it's going to cause
bronchoconstriction
and patients are
going to get a cough.
We used to call it
a captopril cough.
The other thing it
can do is that it can
cause inflammation in
various areas, the mouth,
the tongue, sometimes
even the GI tract.
Patients will say, well, I have
this cough and I
started captopril.
Can I take Robitussin?
That is incorrect.
This has nothing to do with
a virus or an irritation.
This is an adverse effect
of the medication. And
that means the drug needs
to be stopped and you have
to give something else. What
you can give is something
that's going to block
angiotensin 2 at its
receptor. And that's the
angiotensin 1 receptor. That is
blocked by the sartans or
the ARBs. okay the other
thing to note is that
what's common to alaskarin
what's common to the ACE
inhibitors and the ARBs aside
from the angiotensin is
the aldosterone you block
aldosterone it's a yay for
the sodium in the water
you're getting sodium and
water out you want that but
what gets recovered from
the kidney is potassium.
So all of these are going to
cause some degree
of hyperkalemia.
If you're on other medications
that affect potassium
levels, that's when the
problem comes. Because
remember, too much potassium
can change action potential
in the heart. So you need
to be mindful of that.
The adverse effects
of the RAS drugs.
First whether it's
the sin drugs, I would
always tell my patients
in the first few days,
be mindful when you rise.
Because what could
happen is they get that
effect where they can
feel dizzy, almost
like that orthostasis,
and they can fall.
That holds true when
they start the medication
and if they get a
bumping up of their dose.
Blocking aldosterone
will cause hyperkalemia.
the bradykinin cough is
true to ACE inhibitors
you'll have to
replace it with an ARP
drug interactions so again
if you're taking NSAIDs or
you're taking other potassium
sparing diuretics like
Sperano which is often times
the case you need to be
mindful with the potassium
story and you also want to
draw out potassium levels
when you see the patient,
okay?
Renal artery stenosis
is a contraindication.
Now, renal artery
stenosis is rare, but what
happens is that in
renal artery stenosis,
angiotensin II in the
efferent arterial, efferent E,
ACE-E and SEDS-A,
that maintains the patient's
glomerular filtration
rate. So those patients
actually need angio-2.
So if you gave
them one of these
drugs, they can go
into renal failure.
So that is a true
contraindication
of these medications.
But the thing is, that
mechanism is actually nice
if you have a diabetic.
because if you're blocking
angio-2 in the efferent
and you're lowering GFR,
you're actually preserving
the patient's kidney
function. You get a slowing
down of the renal activity
and they're going to see
less albumin in their urine.
Okay, so you'll see
later, and I will
flesh this out
again in the spring,
that ACE inhibitors are
also very beneficial at
protecting the kidneys
in the diabetic patient.
In pregnancy,
these drugs are a no.
They actually, when
they're given in the second
and third trimester, they
can affect the development
of the renal system in
the fetus. So if you
have a patient in pregnancy
who has hypertension,
you're better off with
methyl dopa or libetalol.
The ACE inhibitors that
are the best for CHF
seem to be, and these are
the ones most studied,
ramipril, enalapril,
and lisinopril.
And then alaskirin is a
direct renin inhibitor.
It's going to have
similar effects with
respect to increasing
hyperkalemia because,
again, it's also going
to block aldosterone.
Now, I will say that
what you might see in
practice is going to
be a little different.
ACE inhibitors are the
way to go, but some
physicians sometimes don't
want to deal with the
fact that ACE inhibitors
can cause the cough.
And they may give a sartan
because they know that
the sartans are going
to work just as well.
And the other thing
is they're all
available generically.
So it's not an
insurance problem
as it was before.
So there's nothing
wrong with them doing
that. But I will
say that on boards,
first line is always
going to be the
ACE inhibitors.
That's just of note.
if you get angioedema
it can be sometimes scary
especially if the person
has a swollen tongue
number one, you're going
to remove the ACE inhibitor
that's number one
you can treat the patient
with an antihistamine
you may need epineprin, a
glucocorticoid to stop the
allergic response and
then there is a medication
icotibant This is a
bradykinin receptor blocker.
It's usually used for
hereditary angioedema where
the patient has a
dysfunction of C1 esterase.
And they will, in fact,
have an increase,
these patients, of
bradykinin, and that
increases angioedema.
So those patients that
have this deficiency get
this medication. They do
say that this can help the
patients that have ACI
-induced angioedema as well.
Ica-tybant.
Okay, nitric oxide donors.
Nitroglycerin, nitroprusside,
isosorbide, amyl nitrate. Okay,
remember, they're
going to increase
nitric oxide into the
smooth muscle cell.
you're going to get
an increase in guanile
cyclase increased
cyclic GMP and that's
going to cause smooth
muscle relaxation
that's great you reduce the
patient's blood pressure
but there can be some
things that can happen you
can get that invocation
of sympathetics and you
can get some high heart
rate so you need to be
mindful of that because
usually in CHF they already
have high heart rates So
you need to be mindful.
The other thing is we talked
about PDE3 block
with milrinone.
We have PDE5 with
drugs like sidenafil.
If the patient is taking
a nitrate, gets sidenafil,
and you're getting a
blockade of PDE5, which is
responsible for breaking
this one down, That means
now you're going to have
so much cyclic GMP, so
much muscle relaxation,
and that's the interaction
that will occur between
nitrates and drugs for ED.
Hydralazine is
specific. It does
increase cyclic
GMP, and so it does
Nasiratide. Niceretide
was used years ago.
It would increase cyclic GMP.
They used to use it in
various cases of CHF.
But what happened is
that niceretide was shown
to be hard on the
kidneys and it was
discontinued. So you might
see it here and there.
Basically, it's an increase of
cyclic GMP was its mechanism.
Nitric oxide preload decreased.
decreases the venous return.
By doing that, you decrease
oxygen consumption.
You do decrease the
workload of the heart.
Adverse effects
can be tolerance,
headache, and hypotension.
Because, again,
when you vasodilate
in the head, cerebral arteries,
you're going to
get more headache.
makes sense because
how we manage
migraines is by
giving sumatriptan.
Sumatriptan is a
serotonin agonist and that
causes vasoconstriction
and that makes people
feel better from the
headache. But we know
that patients that take
too much sumatriptan
can get a angina episode
because of that
vasoconstriction that happens.
nitroprusside is actually
beneficial because
not only does it
decrease the preload
it also decreases
afterload because it has
some function at
dilating the arterioles.
So dilating arterioles
is going to reduce your
afterload but nitroprusside
does have the cyanide groups
attached to it and remember
with cyanide if you
have a patient taking
this medication and maybe
cannot doesn't have like
adequate renal function to
take care of the cyanide
groups they can actually go
into cyanide toxicity and
that has to do with the
fact that cyanide, and this
is important if you are
thinking about toxicity
questions on the boards,
does inhibit cytochrome C
oxidase in the mitochondria.
So in the electron
transport chain, you're
going from an aerobic
to an anaerobic process.
The way we manage
is mainly by giving
hydroxycobalamin. This is
a vitamin B12 formulation.
It will bind the
circulating cyanide and
create something
called cyanocobalamin,
which is another
form of vitamin B12.
So either you use
it or you can let
it go in your urine
because, remember,
B vitamins and C
are water-soluble.
Hydralazine is specific
for the arterial.
So it's going to
decrease afterload.
In patients that
have preeclampsia,
it can be used right
before delivery.
It's acetylated, just like
procainamide, isoniazid,
and sulfonamides. And that
means that in the slow
acetylator, it can build up and
cause the butterfly rash and
the myalgia. And that's
known as drug-induced lupus.
The effects, again, can be
headache, flushing, dizziness.
And remember, with the
hypotension, you invoke
sympathetics, which can cause
tachycardia. And you also will
invoke RAS, which again
will invoke aldosterone to
cause recovery of sodium and
water and fluid retention.
So again, you could use
this, but again, you
have to watch the patient.
You have to watch their
heart rate. You have to
watch this whole idea
of their edema. Do they
need perhaps to get some
beta blocker? Do they
need to get a diuretic?
So this is a good picture.
Again, when we're talking
about the medications
here, we know that
we want to use the
cardioselective beta 1
adrenergic receptor antagonist.
You know, alpha-1, mostly
used for BPH, just as a
review, because if you
block the alpha receptors
in the smooth muscle of the
bladder, now the patient
can urinate. So that's
why we use it for BPH.
Kidneys, we have the
thiazides, the loops, and I'll
go through them in a
moment. We talked about the
RAS drugs and the fact
that they will both block
angio-2 and aldosterone,
which is a very good thing.
These here, the
vasomotor ones, remember,
they're not widely
used. I think methyl
dopa is probably the
one that we use mostly
for pregnancy-induced
blood pressure.
and then remember
clonidine, guanabenz,
guanfacine can sometimes
be used for neurological
conditions. They could
use it for ADHD and maybe
if you had somebody
that was going through
withdrawal clonidine
sometimes works nicely because
it can reduce blood
pressure and heart rate.
So beta-1 adrenergic
antagonists are used a lot in
cardiology because they
decrease heart rate, cardiac
output. In the juxtacumaria
apparatus, they also
reduce renin. So it's not
like a RAS drug, but it does
have that potential to
bind renin from its start.
The drugs that
are mostly used in
congestive heart
failure is going to be
metoprolol, bisoproprolol,
and carvetilol.
And carvetilol is
interesting because
it has both alpha
and beta blockade.
So it'll bring down the
blood pressure because it's
an alpha blocker. But if
you are concerned about
the reflexive tachycardia,
which you don't want in
a CHF patient, it has the
beta blockade on board.
Beta 2 is not really used.
Why? Because beta-2 can
cause contraction in the
bronchioles, and that can
cause bronchoconstriction
and worsen asthma, COPD.
In the diabetic, it can
stop the conversion of
glycogen to glucose, and
that can cause hypoglycemia.
And then in somebody
that has atherosclerosis,
if you're binding the
beta-2 receptors in the
arteries there, you can
get more vasoconstriction,
and that can create a
worsening of that problem.
Pindolol and esbutolol have
intrinsic sympathomimetic
action. So in cardiology,
if anything, they can
worsen MI, angina, and even
congestive heart failure.
Esmolol is ultra-short-acting.
Nabivolol also has a
nitric oxide effect. So
there's some vasodilatory
effect with nabivalol.
But these three are the
main drugs used for CHF.
Okay, so AV node
suppressants, we went
through them in the
antiarrhythmic lecture.
One thing to note here is
that sometimes you can use
the dipenes because they
are arterial vasodilators.
They may help with the
reduction of the afterload, but
they're not as widely
used because we have ACE
inhibitors and ARBs. One thing
is verapamil and diltiazem
should not be used for CHF.
And the reason being is
even though they may be
negative coronotropic, they
do reduce the heart rate.
They're negative inotropic.
So they can affect the
heart's pumping capability.
so diuretics it's very
important to understand that
we do have three groups that
can be used for managing
CHF of course not carbonic
and hydrous inhibitors if
anything these are going
to be for mountain sickness
because you're blowing
off carbon dioxide they
can be used for glaucoma
they can be used
for alkalizing the
urine not used here okay
that's going to be
something like acetazolamide
loops will work in the
loop of henley okay
diazides work in the
distal convoluted tubule
and then in the
collecting duct you have
number one the
aldosterone blockers like
spironolactone and then
triamterine and amelioride
not much going on there
they do block the the sodium
channels there, the ENAX,
but they're not really
going to be so useful at
maintaining CHF. Remember,
those drugs are really
there to prevent the loss of
potassium that you get from
using hydrochlorothiazide.
Aldosterone blockers
are known as
mineral corticoid
receptor antagonists.
There's three of them, Sperano,
Apelonone, and a newer
one known as Feneronone.
All of them will antagonize
aldosterone receptors.
So what does that mean?
They're going to
get rid of sodium
and water, which is
a good thing, but
they're going to
recover potassium.
Speranolactone is also an
androgen blocker, and it
can be used for certain
conditions like acne or
hirsutism. And this is an
interesting one because we do
have patients that see the
dermatologist and I had
a patient who was taking,
I guess, retinoids and
medication for their skin
and it wasn't working. and
they were put on spironolactone
and they came to me
and they also showed me a
prescription to go to the
lab to check potassium
levels and they asked me if
this is correct and I'm
like yes that is correct
because this drug that you
you are taking can increase
your potassium so that's
definitely um something
that has to be noted so if
you are not a cardiologist
and your patient needs
spironolactone for her
suturism, which refers to
the fact that the patient is
getting excessive hair that
is due to hormone excess.
They may need to have
periodic potassium checks.
So hyperkalemia,
interesting.
Why do the patients have
acidosis? Well, I like
to say very simply that if
potassium gets recovered,
so does hydrogen ion.
And the opposite will be
true when you lose
potassium, so does hydrogen.
So why is that?
Well, very simply
because aldosterone is blocked.
And basically that's
saying that you're
going to impair your
hydrogen secretion.
So potassium and
hydrogen get recovered
through this
aldosterone blockade.
Spironolactone will cause
the gynecomastia and
impotence because it's
blocking androgens. So again,
patients may appear to have
an increase in their chest.
Impotence can happen.
I think first aid has a
great way in mnemonic.
Some drugs create awesome
knockers. And that stands
for speranolactone,
digoxin, as I just mentioned,
I believe ketoconazole.
You'll read it when you
get to first aid, but
that's a great way to
remember this for your boards.
Drug interactions,
the renin drugs, of
course, and also NSAIDs and
digoxin. Why digoxin? Well,
remember, when we talked
about digoxin, we talked a
lot about the hypokalemia.
But remember,
think about how digoxin works.
it will inhibit the
sodium potassium
ATPase. By blocking
that enzyme, you
actually can increase
your, itself,
you can increase your
potassium in your blood.
This is, you know, irregardless
of taking a diuretic.
The other thing is the
NSAIDs. Very interesting.
What will happen is that
NSAIDs will decrease renal
blood flow and the GFR,
because remember, they block
prestaglandins and the
afranarterial. That vasoconstriction
can actually prevent
potassium from being excreted.
So patients that take
NSAIDs can get hyperkalemia.
Putting it together with
spironolactone can increase
that risk. So if you're
looking for something
that works as a mineral
corticoid receptor blocker
for your CHF patient and
you don't want to increase
gynecomastia, the best
next choice is aprelinone.
Fenirinone is the newest.
It's more selective than
these two at binding to
the minocorticoid receptor.
And it also slows the
progression of CKD, which
stands for kidney disease.
okay and the idea here is
this could be used too but
is going to be more
expensive than the others so
here is exactly how
these drugs work okay
if I was talking to
you about ameloride
or triamterine these
are going to block
here the enac channels
so in the principal
cells you'll see
that sodium and water
will be going out and
potassium stays in.
A nice group of drugs
that you can use if, say,
you're giving the patient
hydrochlorothiazide
and you're worrying
about the hypokalemia.
These drugs, spironolactone,
aprelinone, are going
to bind the aldosterone
receptor here. So they,
too, are going to get rid
of sodium and water and
then potassium gets
recovered. And then in the
intercalated cells, what
you will see is that as
you're getting more potassium
back, so will hydrogen
follow and bicarbonate
is actually going to be
let out. And that makes
sense because that is
another mechanism of how
the acidosis will happen.
The loop diuretics,
they work in
the thick ascending
loop of Henle.
And they're going to
inhibit a specific
transporter known as a
sodium-potassium-2-chloride.
They're high-sealing
diuretics. They also have a
certain degree of having an
effect on the venous return.
So that means they do
reduce preload. And
that makes it a good
option for those
patients that have
congestive heart failure.
There's a few of
them that you have to
know. all of them have
a sulfonamide in their
structure except
ethacrinic acid. And
that is a good thing
to understand because
all of them will have
an effect on hearing.
Okay?
But ethacrinic has
the most effect
on hearing. It's
the most autotoxic.
so with the loops one
thing that we have to
understand is that by
binding to this transport
you're getting rid
of sodium, chloride,
potassium and you're
also having an effect on
all other ions your
calcium, your magnesium
and calcium becomes
interesting in those
patients that, say,
have metastatic cancer.
Patients that have
metastatic cancer are
going to show high levels
of calcium in their
blood as the bone
starts breaking down.
And the way that is
managed is by giving,
oftentimes, something
like furosemide.
When you're low in
magnesium, you're also going
to have a decrease in
something called parathyroid
hormone. And that
also reduces calcium
recovery. So that's another
mechanism of how the
idea of calcium loss
occurs with loop diuretics.
The other thing to note is,
coming forward, the loss
of potassium means that
you're also going to get a
loss of hydrogen ions. You're
going to have alkalosis.
And that has to do
with the fact that when
you get fluid depleted,
you increase RAS.
You increase your
aldosterone, and that means
now you're getting rid
of your potassium and
your hydrogen ion because
you're trying to recover
sodium and water. So
it's almost like a
contradiction, but that's
important to remember.
The other thing is
that loop diuretics
increase prestaglandin,
so there's
some vasodilatory
effects with these.
They are used for
many different things.
Pulmonary edema,
hypercalcemia, as I
mentioned, the metastatic
cancer patient,
hyperkalemia, hypertension,
and acute renal failure.
Some of the adverse
effects, as mentioned,
can be the loss
of all of these.
Also, hyperuricemia. And
that has to do with the
fact now that when we're
talking about organic
acid transport, these
drugs might affect those
transporters and allow
for uric acid recovery.
As I mentioned, ototoxicity,
why is that happening?
Well, a couple of
things, but mainly it
has to do with the
fact that in the
inner ear, there may
be some disruption.
in ions and fluids
so patients can
experience a certain
degree of ototoxicity
especially with ethacrinic
but ethacrinic does not
have the sulfur ion in
it so sulfonamide allergy
photosensitivity is not
going to be as much with
ethacrinic acid as as the
others and then the drug
interactions will be NSAIDs
and again that has to do with
the prostaglandin story
happening in the kidney.
Digoxin, and that's again
the after depolarization
because with loops you're
losing your potassium
and that's going to create
a higher potential for
digoxin doing its job.
And then overlap toxicity,
that applies to cisplatin,
gentamicin, and vanco.
Those drugs are themselves
ototoxic, so if you were taking
say cisplatin for treating
a solid tumor, and you
needed to use furosemide, you
might be at a greater risk
of getting hearing loss.
And now thiazides
work in the distal
convoluted tubule,
and they're going to
block the sodium
chloride transporter.
And they, in fact,
will allow for excretion
of sodium chloride
and potassium. But,
again, when we're
talking about parathyroid
here, there's going
to be a positive
effect, not a negative.
And that would mean that
in the distal convoluted
tubule, you're going to
get a recovery of calcium.
More reabsorption by the DCT.
Because of that, they can use
this medication
for kidney stones.
because instead
of it going to the
bladder and causing
more irritation,
you would want to recover more
of the calcium into the blood.
And then nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus, it
has to do with the fact
that, again, those patients
are going to be using
the bathroom a lot.
And what would it mean
is, again, Again, as you
are going into that case
where you're getting
fluid depleted, you're
increasing RAS again. And
that RAS now is going to
allow for more sodium and
water being recovered.
That's the mechanism. It
sounds somewhat
contradictory, but that is how
it works for the nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus.
The adverse effects, in
many ways, they mirror
the loops with the
hypokalemia and the
alcoholism. So you're getting
rid of your potassium,
and you're getting rid
of the hydrogen ion.
And that, again, has
to do with increasing
RAS, increasing
aldosterone, and you're
recovering, again,
sodium and water, but
you're losing hydrogen
ion and potassium.
Hyperglycemia, again, this
is an effect you need to
know for boards. It's not as
relevant clinically because
usually patients that are
diabetic are taking diabetic
meds and we don't worry so
much. But physiologically,
what will happen is that
if you are hypokalemic,
you're going to have a
reduction in insulin release.
If we're talking about
an increase in lipids,
again, that has to do
with the fact that if
you reduce your insulin
sensitivity, you create
a possibility of increasing
your lipid panel.
Hyperuricemia, again
that goes to the idea
that you're affecting the
organic acid transporters
and that's going to
recover uric acid.
And then the hypovolemia
and hyponatremia make sense.
Sulfa sensitivity,
this is another
group that has sulfa
in its structure.
So if you are allergic,
say, to sulfonamides,
you should not be taking
loops or thiazides.
The other thing, if you
go on some sunny vacation,
you need to wear an
appropriate sunscreen.
And then the drug
interactions, again, VIG,
why? Because you're
lowering your potassium and
you run the risk of the
after depolarization.
NSAIDs, because again,
NSAIDs, you're going to block
prostaglandins. in the
afrenarterial, that's going
to change your GFR and
blood flow. That might run
the risk of now having
an increase in potassium.
And then lithium is interesting
because with lithium,
the idea here is the more
sodium and water that
you lose, but mainly
the sodium, the more
lithium you recover. So
there is a drug interaction
that patients can
become more prone to
lithium toxicity if
they're taking a thiazide.
Iverbradine was mentioned
in the previous lecture.
This is a medication
that will bind the funny
channels or the IF
channels of the heart.
So they will, in fact,
decrease the heart
rate, but they have no
effect on contractility
or repolarization. So,
no effect on the action
potential duration.
They can be used, this drug can
be used for CHF
and stable angina,
especially in those that
cannot take a beta blocker.
and you can see here
the effects on
the funny channels
the adverse effects make sense
bradycardia can occur you
need to be mindful of an AV
node block vision changes
and I explained that in a
previous lecture that this
particular drug can inhibit
retinal ih channels
in the eye and that
would lead now to
patients getting something
called luminous
phenomena where they may
see bright flashes
in their visual field
and then in pregnancy
there's not enough data
to support this medication
and then with sip
inhibitors especially
like something like
grapefruit juice that
can raise the level of
iverbradine and that can
cause more bradycardia.
Some of the other
drugs and the big one
here is called ARNI,
which stands for
angiotensin receptor and
niprolysin inhibitor.
Sagubitril is the niprolysin
inhibitor. It's a pro-drug.
When you inhibit
this particular
protein, what you're
going to do is you're
going to enhance
nitriuretic peptides
and that will now allow
for a loss of sodium and
water. And that's a good
thing if you're dealing
with CHF. This drug has
actually been shown to
improve survival and
decrease hospitalizations in
those people with congestive
heart failure. It is
combined with valsartan
and valsartan is an ARB.
So with that you have
to be concerned with say
hypotension because
remember blocking angio 2 is
going to cause vasodilation
and then of course
the effect on aldosterone
means that yes you're
getting rid of sodium and
water a good thing but
Valsadin allows for the
recovery of the potassium.
We have the SGLT2 inhibitors.
We mainly use
them for diabetes,
but I'll explain why
we can use them and why
they're so effective
for CHF in a moment.
We have Conovapten.
This medication will, in fact,
block vasopressin 1A receptors.
And by doing that, it
decreases peripheral
vascular resistance,
a vasopressin blocker.
And blocking PVR, peripheral
vascular resistance,
means that your blood
pressure will go down.
And this one also
blocks vasopressin 2.
and by doing that it
causes water secretion.
So you're getting a
release of water and you're
also getting a lowering
of blood pressure and
I'll talk about Conovapton
next semester when
we talk about some of
the drugs in endocrine.
And then semaglutide,
it's a GLP-1 agonist.
Very widely used now
not only to improve
insulin sensitivity
because it enhances
insulin secretion and
it blocks glucagon,
but it also can work
to suppress appetite.
So if patients,
for example,
have obesity that is related
or is worsening their
congestive heart failure,
there's some early data
showing that this
medication can help as well.
So, SGLT2 inhibitors,
subtype 2, sodium glucose
transport, they all end in flozin,
the ones that I highlighted
in red are the ones that
have been used for CHF.
What they do is, in the
proximal tubule, when
they block that transporter,
they get rid of glucose.
And that's a good thing
because we're getting
rid of sugar, and that
is helping a diabetic.
But in addition, it's
been shown now that it
can promote the release
of sodium in water.
So, just like what
we saw with the ARBs
and the ARNI and
the ACE inhibitors,
it can reduce both
preload and afterload.
And this is why we're
seeing a lot of protocols
now having this
medication, these
medications on board,
especially if you're diabetic,
because if you're
diabetic, it has been
shown that A1C reduction
is about 1% lower.
That doesn't seem like
much, but if you go from
a 5.6, or maybe in
the diabetic 7 to like
6, that's a significant,
significant decrease.
The one thing is that
it can cause UTIs.
And that would be the reason
is that as you're getting
rid of glucose and it's
going through the bladder,
there may be the potential
for that glucose to kind
of feed some of the microbes
that exist there. So if
the patient is getting
frequent UTIs with these
medications, that might be
an evaluation you need to do.
and then if your creatinine
clearance is less than 30
you need to consider if
you want to give these
medications I think now
they say less than 20
they like lowered the
bar a little bit because
you run the risk that
the patient can go into
a renal failure if
their GFR was that low
so again proximal tubule
it's going to bind
this transporter and you're
getting rid of glucose
and you're getting rid
of sodium and water so it
helps the type 2 diabetic
it helps that patient with
congestive heart failure
so again once more
the ARNI sagubitril
that is going to inhibit
niprolysin and that's
going to raise your
nitriuretic peptides,
and that is going to
allow for the release
of sodium and water
and allow for diureses.
If you're blocking
RAS or you're blocking
the AT1 receptor,
you're going to get
hypotension because you're
blocking angio-2 and
you're also getting a
decrease in, you're
blocking aldosterone, so
you're going to get rid
of sodium and water.
But you will get some
degree of hyperkalemia.
Beresiguanth came to
the market not too
long ago. This is a
medication that, quite
frankly, is going to
increase cyclic GMP.
And remember, cyclic GMP
is going to create smooth
muscle relaxation, and
we want that. But it's
not going to do so through
donating nitric oxide.
It's independent
of nitric oxide.
The adverse effects are
going to be similar, however.
You will get some
headache, dizziness,
the hypotension, and the
reflexive tachycardia.
Because again, the more
you relax your smooth
muscle and you lower
your blood pressure,
baroreceptor reflex
mechanism comes in and
creates sympathetics to
increase your heart rate
they do say you should
not give this with a
nitric oxide donor and
it makes sense because
all of these effects
the headache, dizziness,
hypotension and tachycardia
will be potentiated
or no PDE5s and that's
true because if you gave
say like ****** with
this one you're going to
enhance cyclic GMP and
you're going to get the
same outcome, severe
hypotension and tachycardia.
One thing it does is that
since it's not giving
nitric oxide, you're
not going to get
tolerance. So you don't
have to have a window of
nitrate-free period
with these medications.
And then overall, they
saw that it reduced
hospitalizations
in patients with
worsened chronic
congestive heart failure.
And remember,
again, this is a newer
drug, so you may not see
it too much right now
as opposed to the other
medications. So in
summary, if we're talking
about improving symptoms,
we want to give ACE,
ARBs, ARNIs,
the SGLT2 inhibitors, the
mineral corticoid antagonist.
If we're talking
about survival, the
main difference
is the diuretics.
The diuretics help the
symptoms, and that makes
sense. If you have edema
and you can't move because
your ankles are too swollen
or your GI is full of
fluid, that does help the
patient. It helps relieve
some of that fluid, makes
them maybe breathe better.
But one thing to
note is that that one
will not help with
the survival. For
survival, we go back
to beta blockers,
RAS drugs,
the flozins,
mineral corticoid, and maybe
hydrolazine with the nitrate.
And again, with the
hydrolazine, that's
the one that's
for the afterload.
Nitrate is for the preload.
So in summary, reduced
cardiac output.
you get an increase
in sympathetics
you want to give a beta blocker
you're going to get an
increase in RAS so that's
where all the renin
drugs will come into play
cardiac remodeling
the RAS drugs help and
so do the beta blockers
again the diuretics will
help with some of the
symptoms related to
sodium and water retention
but on their own they're
not going to prolong
survival And remember,
diuretics are also going
to introduce adverse
effects, especially if
we're talking about the
idea of electrolytes, such
as potassium, calcium,
things of that nature.
I will be doing a question
review, but I wanted
to go back to the previous
topic on the arrhythmias
with this patient
having a diagnosis of a
ventricular arrhythmia
and started on medication.
several months later
she presented with
excessive fatigue, weight
gain, hair loss and
dry skin she has a low
T4 and an elevated TSH
so looking at the low
T4 and elevated TSH
and the fact that she's
got a slowing down
of her system, this is
showing us that it's
probably due to a
hypothyroidism and looking
at this question, we
know that we have to look
for something that is
an anti-arrhythmic.
So is it disopiramide?
No, disopiramide is
a 1A anti-arrhythmic
and this one is going to
prolong the action
potential and it does
have an effect at
prolonging repolarization
because it does block
the potassium channels.
But disapyramide can also
cause a proarrhythmic
effect because it blocks
the muscarinic receptors.
So disapyramide is
mostly associated with an
anti-muscarinic profile.
So urinary retention,
perhaps an arrhythmia because
you're increasing
AV node action,
perhaps glaucoma,
constipation, dryness.
Lidocaine is the 1B.
This is the one that is
working on tissue that
has been depolarized
already. So it will help
prevent the arrhythmias
in those patients
that have had an MI.
Lidocaine, if anything,
is going to shorten
the action potential.
It lowers the QT.
Again, another good
option post-MI, but it
will probably cause
more of a neurological
effect because it is
itself an anesthetic.
Propanolol is beta-1, beta-2.
This is a class 2
antiarrhythmic. It's
going to shorten
the phase 4 slope.
And it works very nicely
at the SA node. It's
an AV node suppressant.
But beta-1, beta-2, I
would worry about the
lungs. I would worry about
glucose levels and
peripheral vascular disease.
Amiodarone is probably
the best answer.
And this is the one
that's iodinated.
So it itself can cause
hyperthyroidism. Or in this
case, it probably stopped
the conversion of T4 to T3.
And we need T3 as the active
form of thyroid hormone.
Amiodarone can also
cause pulmonary fibrosis,
corneal deposits,
effects in the liver.
It can inhibit SIP.
And the other thing
with amiodarone,
it has all the
receptor mechanisms.
It can act as a beta
blocker, as an alpha blocker.
It can also inhibit sodium,
potassium, of course,
and calcium channels. and
then diltiazem is a class
4 antiarrhythmic this is
the one that's a calcium
channel blocker as opposed
to the dipenes diltiazem
and rapamil do not affect
as much the arterial roles
they're going to be specific
for the SA and AV node
of the heart while the
dipenes do not have an effect
on the cardiac muscle so
D in fact is going to be
the best answer here thank
you for your attention
I will be doing a question
review to go through these
concepts I encourage you
to give it a look so it
can help you digest this
lecture a little bit more
thank you for your attention
and I'll see you soon